[{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "first four decisive years for lutheranism", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1517-20", "id": 1},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "maritime area dominated by hanseatic league after 1350", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "baltic and north seas", "id": 2},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "cause of italy's decline", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "franco-spanish wars late 15th century", "id": 3},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "natural industries centered in germany", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "mining, metal, armament", "id": 4},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "security of the fuggers", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "tyrol mines leased from habsburgs", "id": 5},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "fuggers and welsers where from", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "augsburg", "id": 6},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "reformation artists and printers", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "L cranach, A durer and froben of basel", "id": 7},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "outlying empire disconnected portions", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "swiss confederacy, netherlands, bohemia, milan", "id": 8},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "source of habsburg's quasi-hereditary strength", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "upper rhine, austria", "id": 9},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what/when did maximilian I add to habsburg domains by marriage", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1493-1519 free county of burgundy, brabant, flanders, artois, luxembourg", "id": 10},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "3 spiritual imperial electors", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "cologne mainz trier", "id": 11},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "4 secular electors", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "bohemia brandenburg saxony palatinate", "id": 12},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "which of the 85 imperial cities acquired extensive lands, patrician rule", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "nuremburg", "id": 13},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "location of armed swabian league", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "southwest", "id": 14},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "most notable victims of fourteenth century agrarian crisis", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "imperial knights (reichsritter)", "id": 15},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "backbone of the swabian league", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "franz von sickingen", "id": 16},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "knight leader in peasants' war", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "gotz von berlichingen", "id": 17},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "humanist utopian knight", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "ulrich von hutton", "id": 18},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "where was german peasantry armed and fairly free", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "south (austria, switzerland)", "id": 19},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "cause of inflation that pressed peasants here and all over western europe", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "increased mining yields, vigorous trade", "id": 20},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "specific german problems", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "lack of national unity, many lords, grasping churches", "id": 21},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "location of peasant risings", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "lake constance, black forest, wurtemburg, carinthia, styria", "id": 22},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "radical regions symbolized by bundschuh", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "alsace, upper rhine", "id": 23},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "peasant allies", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "urban artisans , lesser craftsman in small towns", "id": 24},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "more hated than lay lords", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "ecclesiastical lords and jewish lenders", "id": 25},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "why was the church hated in germany", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "an aristocracy of territorial rulers, many grasping lower clergy, demanding papacy", "id": 26},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "examples of prince-bishops who held one fifth of the realm", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "mainz magdeburg munster wurzburg salzburg", "id": 27},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "nominated bishops of geneva", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "dukes of savoy", "id": 28},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "called pope in his own lands", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "duke of cleves", "id": 29},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "medieval disasters of fourteenth century", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "plague, war economic decline", "id": 30},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "sources of german mystic tradition", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "meister eckhard, john tauler", "id": 31},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "whose imitation of christ obediently stressed inner life", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "thomas a kempis", "id": 32},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "where did millenarian radicalism break out most frequently", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "netherlands (industrial flanders)", "id": 33},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what woman-taking movement did this culminate in", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "free brethren of fifteenth century", "id": 34},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "exemplary german heretic in this vein (burned, fed bundschuh)", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "drummer of niklashausen", "id": 35},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "erasmus life", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1466-1536", "id": 36},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "when was his greek new testament", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1516", "id": 37},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what terms did he gloss", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "ecclesia, presbyter", "id": 38},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "champion of jewish books against pfeffercorn's attempted imperial burning", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "john reuchlin", "id": 39},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "satirical anti-dominican publication in this battle", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "letters of obscure men (von hutten et al)", "id": 40},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what did german humanists control", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "schools, universities, administration", "id": 41},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "on what did humanists concentrate in england, france and italy", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "educating the aristocracy and producing gentlemen", "id": 42},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "which humanist saved luther from papal summons in 1518", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "george spalatin", "id": 43},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what outcome of reformation was hard to predict", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "decline of towns and peasants", "id": 44},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "papacy of soft and kindly pope Leo X", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1513-21", "id": 45},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "dates of great schism", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1378-1417", "id": 46},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "charles v born", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1500", "id": 47},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "on father philip's death what title was gained", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "burgundy (franche comte, luxemburg, netherlands)", "id": 48},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what did grandfather ferdinand bequeath in 1516", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "aragon, sicily, naples, castile+america", "id": 49},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what austrian lands did grandfather maximilian bequeath", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "austria, tyrol, styria, carinthia, carniola", "id": 50},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "where were original habsburg lands", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "upper rhine between switzerland and burgundy", "id": 51},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "other imperial candidates", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "henry viii, francis i, frederick of saxony", "id": 52},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "charles' brilliant chancellor", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "mercurino de gattinari", "id": 53},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what ruler inspired charles", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "charlemagne", "id": 54},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "when had france lost burgundy", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1477", "id": 55},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what habsburg counties owed feudal allegiance to france", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "artois and flanders", "id": 56},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "other sources of tension", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "navarre, sicily, naples, milan", "id": 57},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "charles' position in italy", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "secure in south, endangered in north by french victory at marignano(1515)", "id": 58},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "technical fiefs of empire", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "milan and independent savoy", "id": 59},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what region had inspired empire vs france clash for centuries", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "alsace / lorraine", "id": 60},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what ended the forty year habsburg-valois struggle", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "peace of cateau-cambresis (1559)", "id": 61},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what city and admiral helped charles on mediterranean sea", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "genoa, Andrea Doria", "id": 62},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what event freed ottomans to dispute the mediterranean", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "conquest of rhodes (1522)", "id": 63},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what did charles brother ferdinand inherit in 1526", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "hungary, bohemia", "id": 64},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "Rule of Sulaimon the great", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1520-1566", "id": 65},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "charles tutor who died in 1521", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "guillaume de chievres", "id": 66},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "charles secretary for spain and italy", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "francisco de los cobos", "id": 67},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "secretary for burgundy and germany", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "nicolas perrenot, lord of granvelle", "id": 68},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what supplied charles with many administrators", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "franche comte", "id": 69},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what supplied charles with industrial wealth", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "flanders, brabant, hainault", "id": 70},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what undermined flanders and caused uprisings", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "english cloth industry, heavy burgundian taxes", "id": 71},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "who had revolted against maximilian?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "bruges and ghent", "id": 72},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what popular revolt did charles put down in 1540?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "ghent", "id": 73},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what did flanders' decline help?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "brabant / antwerp (Scheldt port)", "id": 74},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what began antwerp's commercial dominance of europe", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "portuguese transfer there of spice staple in 1504", "id": 75},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what ended antwerp's commercial dominance of europe", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "habsburg bankruptcy in 1557", "id": 76},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what were antwerps economic bases", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "cloth finishing, metal work, trade from baltic down rhine, currency", "id": 77},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "what complicated charles policy in netherlands", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "getting cooperation from provincial estates (they ratified estates general)", "id": 78},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what netherlands possessions did charles add", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "tournai friesland overijssel utrecht groningen ", "id": 79},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what province did france incite against charles", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "guelders (egmont counts)", "id": 80},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "rather independent prince-bishoprics", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "liege, utrecht", "id": 81},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "spain grew no richer despite these 3 economic advantages", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "wool production, cloth exports, incoming bullion", "id": 82},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what commercial center decayed", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "valencia (following granada)", "id": 83},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "some life was shown where", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "valencia and seville", "id": 84},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "where did charles quadruple taxes", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "castile", "id": 85},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what towns formed a revolutionary government (germania) broken in 1523", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "valencia", "id": 86},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what rebellious league formed in castile in 1520", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "comuneros", "id": 87},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "what social classes supported charles in spain", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "church and nobles", "id": 88},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what council provided unified government for spain", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "castilian", "id": 89},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what limited charles absolutism", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "power of the cortes, noble semi-independence, customary traditions", "id": 90},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what favored absolutism", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "destruction of urban liberties", "id": 91},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "cortes lands at vera cruz", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1519", "id": 92},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "cortes conquers mexixo", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1521", "id": 93},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "pizarros conquer incan peru", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1530", "id": 94},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "who asserted that war against indians required just cause", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "francisco de vitoria", "id": 95},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "what and when was the encomienda system replaced by royal rule from a distance in south/central america", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1542, new laws of the indies", "id": 96},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "was there a lutheran party by 1521?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "no", "id": 97},{"show": "q", "color": "color3", "question": "what began the reformation?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "luthers appearance at diet of worms", "id": 98},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what edict was issued at worms", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "denunciation of lutheran heresy", "id": 99},{"show": "q", "color": "color4", "question": "who erratically took over when luther left wittenburg (not melanchthon)?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "Andrew Carlstadt", "id": 100},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "who did radicals turn toward", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "zwickau prophets", "id": 101},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "who called luther back", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "moderates", "id": 102},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "where was lutheran worship developed", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "saxony", "id": 103},{"show": "q", "color": "color5", "question": "when did luther marry catherine von bora", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "1525", "id": 104},{"show": "q", "color": "color0", "question": "what prince succeeded frederick the wise", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "elector john", "id": 105},{"show": "q", "color": "color1", "question": "who made up the Visitation", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "two electoral councillors and two theologians", "id": 106},{"show": "q", "color": "color2", "question": "what spurred the self-interest of territorial rulers?", "difficulty": 5, "answer": "confiscation of Church land (often owned by regular orders)", "id": 107}]